all right hello and welcome this is
active inference math stream number 10.1
March 28th
2024 or 29th not exactly sure and we're
here with Thomas Farley discussing
generalized decomposition of
multivariate information there will be a
presentation followed by a discussion so
Thomas thank you very much for joining
looking forward to this and everyone's
questions yeah thank you for having me
I'm really excited to get to talk about
this um with uh people who are also
interested and I think it's the 29th
because I compiled this latch last night
was the last time I compiled it so I
think it's a one day out of sync all
right and so yeah so I'll be talking
today about generalized decomposition of
multivari information this is sort of
walking through a paper that I recently
published in um plus one and I'll have a
link to that at the end of the talk if
you you know want to read more um sort
of interested in what I've covered here
and so um we'll start with a a little
bit of a background sort of the
intuitions around information Theory and
then introducing these two ideas of the
partial information decomposition and a
partial entropy decomposition and I
can't see who's in the audience but you
know if you are an expert in
multivariate information Theory you can
just go watch YouTube videos for five
minutes or so um while we get everybody
else up to stream and then um once we've
got sort of all the necessary
mathematical Machinery built um then
I'll talk about how I can how I've taken
the PID and the ped and sort of
generalize them to this thing I'm
calling the G the generalized
information decomposition which is based
on the um the cach Leer Divergence and
once we've kind of built that um we'll
talk a little bit about how uh the G can
be used to get insight into other
information theoretic measures you know
um well-known things like the total
correlation or the ton sporns adelement
complexity and then finally um to show
that it is you know truly a generalize
generalization of the PID um I'll
actually walk through the derivation of
the classic Williams and beer byari
partial information decomposition from
the generalized information
decomposition and there are actually
some kind of interesting um sort of
mathematical questions that kind of that
that you discover as you do that
derivation that you know I'll talk a a
little bit about then I have a brief
section at the end sort of talking about
sort of future work what um we could do
with this and since this is the active
inference stream you know I'll end with
a little bit of discussion of sort of
predictive coding in neuroscience and
then I would be really interested in
talking um in some way to people in the
audience who might be more expert in
active inference or free energy than I
am you know because there you know maybe
things that could be done with this that
are not uh super obvious to me just
because I'm sort of coming at this from
a slightly different angle so um with
that in mind uh let's get started
background so um you know this is the
active inference Stream So I sort of
assume that we're all familiar with uh
sort of information Theory and complex
systems you know it's really I think
become the case that information theory
is uh sort of emerging as a lingua
franka for complex systems right um it's
non-parametric it's model free uh which
makes it very useful for complex or you
know nonlinear systems that are not well
modeled just by you know linear
regressions um it has some really deep
and interesting connections to
thermodynamics that I won't talk about
here but you know that's something I
think is really interesting and there's
some very cool work pushing that forward
and then what makes it most relevant for
uh complex systems is that it really
elegantly handles multivariate
interactions right you know it's hard to
sort of imagine what a what a five way
peon correlation might look like besides
just a a covariance matrix of of pawise
correlations but information Theory can
really handle multivar interactions sort
of on their own terms okay and then so
I'm sure again we're all familiar that
the basic object of study is this thing
called the entropy this is Shannon's
classic entropy function negative sum of
P log P I introduce a little bit of
notation here so Random variables uh I
will be denoting with um italic
uppercase italics the support set so
that is to say all of the states that
you know tala size X can take will be
indicated with the um math Cal
caligraphic font and then the specific
state that you know X is all the
elements of the support set I denote
with um lowercase
italics all right and so you know as we
as we you know continue to leverage this
notation this distinction between sort
of average General random variables and
their specific local instances is going
to be quite important right so classic
Shannon information we're just iterating
over all of the possible states that X
can take and Computing the probability
of that state times the log of the
probability of that state okay and so
this quantifies sort of our average
uncertainty about the state of X right
you know if you were to
um take X you know it was a coin say
you're a coin that you were flipping you
know it quantifies how uncertain are you
about the state of X you know um and
from this we build you know the classic
Mutual information Shannon Mutual
information is a pairwise measure of
correlation and it is um arguably I
think the most fundamental one of the
most fundamental ideas in modern
information Theory and so you know we
would read this as you know the
information that X discloses about y or
ultimately the information that y
discloses about X is the difference
between our initial uncertainty about X
so this is you know the entropy of X and
then we subtract off the uncertainty
about X that remains after we have
learned y right so this is the the
conditional entropy here and um when I
when I teach this in class you know I
like to think you know we start with
some big pile of uncertainty we scoop
some uncertainty out when we learn why
and so we have a slightly smaller pile
of uncertainty left the difference
between you know the big pile and the
small pile is the amount of uncertainty
that we scooped out right that's the the
uncertainty that is resolved by learning
why
okay and so you know since we're we're
all big fans of sort of basian thinking
here you know um I like to think of this
you know our initial uncertainty about X
this is our prior right um this is the
uncertainty about X that sort of we come
into without having learned anything
okay then we observe Y and we compute a
new uncertainty about X and that is our
posterior
uncertainty uh about X after learning
why and thinking about this in terms of
priors and pro posteriors is really
helpful because this is just a
particular case of a prior posterior
relationship right you could um sort of
heuristically propose a more General uh
definition of information it's just the
difference between a prior uncertainty
and a posterior uncertainty and how you
sort of formally specify the prior and
the posterior is uh sort of largely up
to you okay and so mutual information is
just the special case of this broader
definition where the prior and posterior
are related by this by these sort of
joint marginal
relationships okay but again it's just a
special case of this much larger sort of
definition and we're going to come back
to this come back to this in a moment
okay but continuing on sort of our
information theoretic background you can
do the multivariant mutual information
if you want so here now we have two
sources X1 and X2 that are together
disclosing information about why right
and again you have our prior which is
just our uncertainty about Y and then
we're going to subtract off the
uncertainty about y that remains after
learning X1 and X2 okay so far so good
any questions Dan in the chat people
hanging on for dear life good all right
um and so when you start looking at like
multivariant Mutual information um
things can get really interesting really
fast right and so like the the first
thing is that you know this Mutual
information the information that X1 and
X2 disclose about Y is not trivially
reducible to the sum of the mutual
informations right the mutual
information that X1 and X2 disclose
about Y is not equal to not generally
let's say equal to the information that
X1 discloses about y plus the
information that X2 discloses about y
right the whole in this case X1 and X2
is not trivially reducible to the sum of
the parts okay and you can have both
cases right if the joint Mutual
information is less than the sum of the
marginal Mutual informations then what
that tells us is that there is
information about y that is duplicated
over X1 and X2 and so when you sum the
two together independently you are
double counting that information right
and so this is what we call redundancy
right it's the information about why
that is copied over both of the inputs
and gets you know double counted when
you add them
together arguably the more interesting
case is the opposite right the case
where the whole the information that X1
and X2 disclos about y jointly is
greater than the sum of the two marginal
m ual informations okay and if you're
familiar with uh uh that should be y not
Z I apologize that's a typo um and so if
you're familiar with sort of like
integrated information Theory some of
the stuff that Julio ton has been doing
you know you s of might recognize this
is as something like integrated
information all right it's information
that is in the whole as the joint state
of X1 and X2 that is not present in the
sum of the parts okay and so you know
people call that like I said integrated
information we're going to call it here
Synergy all right and so we have these
two sort of interesting things that are
happening we got a three-way interaction
between X1 X2 and Y and it has like two
different it can have two different
flavors this redundancy which is
duplicated information and then Synergy
which is information that is only
accessible in the whole and not any of
the parts okay um and so you know if we
if we sort of take these two ideas um we
can kind of make them a little bit more
formal and a little bit more rigorous by
noticing that um we can talk about them
in terms of logical connectives okay so
redundancy I like to think of as that
information that could be learned by
observing X1 or X2 or X3 or you know as
many X's as you have in the in your data
set right and so for instance if um X1
and X2 are just you know linked by a
copy gate you know X2 is just a copy of
X1 then you could look at either one on
its own and get all of the information
right because they are just copies of
each
other in contrast um Synergy is
information that can only be learned by
observing X1 and X2 and X3 and yada yada
yada okay
um and you know this link between
logical connectives and higher order
information uh lets us do like really
interesting things like we can construct
very exotic combinations of information
and this will come up more when we talk
about the information decomposition but
you could ask for instance okay what
information could only be learned by
observing X1 and X2 or X3 and X4 right
and so you know we're starting to see
like what the structure of you know
multivariate information might look like
it's going to be these um sort of chains
of um Atomic it's going to be these
chains of sort of atomic subsets of the
collection of inputs joined by logical
connectives ANS and ores okay um any
questions about this because get this
this link between redundancy and Synergy
and ores and ANS is very helpful for
thinking about what's to come so far so
good Okay cool so um this brings us to
the partial information decomposition
all right and so the idea is that we
would like to take um this joint Mutual
information uh the information that X1
and X2 disclose about
why and these Atomic components that
resolves this uh ambiguity about the
relationship between the parts and the
holes right remember we said that the
sum of the two marginal Mutual
informations can be greater than or less
than the joint Mutual information right
so you know how can we um extract a
relationship that sort of brings all of
these into harmony okay and the way
we're going to do this is with um this
sort of branch of modern information
Theory called the P ID partial
information de composition what it does
is it takes the mutual information that
that two you know that X1 and X2 just
close at Y and it breaks it down into
the redundancy so this would be the
information about y that could be
learned by observing X1 alone or X2
alone plus the Synergy so this would be
the information about why that can only
be learned when X1 and X2
are known together and then these two
unique terms right which is the
information about why that can only be
learned uh when observing X1 or only
learned when observing X2 and then to
force um Harmony between the joint and
the marginal Mutual informations we will
also say that the marginal Mutual
information should be decomposed in the
same way so even though you know the
information that X1 discloses about y
makes no obvious reference to X2 you
know there is still that redund
information about why that could be
learned by observing X1 or X2 plus the
unique information from X1 and likewise
for X2
okay and I'm sure many of you have seen
these um this kind of classic vent
diagram this goes back to the original
Williams and beer paper but I find that
it's really helpful to sort of build the
intuition here right so the big oval is
the joint Mutual information uh the two
circles are the marginal mut Mutual
informations and then so we have the
redundancy is the overlap between the
two marginal Mutual informations the
unique information is the difference
between the marginal Mutual informations
and the redundancy and then this purple
Synergy is the sort of extra special
sauce that you get uh in the whole
Mutual information that is not you know
uh present in either of the two uh the
two marginal Mutual informations all
right and so um you know this is a
a very restricted case you know we just
have two inputs and one target y but I
find it's really helpful for sort of
getting a handle on the the underlying
logic of this thing okay but of course
we typically are not looking at us at
systems that just have two inputs in one
target uh we often have many many
systems and so you know there is a
general case uh for the PID and you can
take for an arbitrary number of inputs
you know X1 to XK all just exposing
information about why it can always be
decomposed into a finite set of atoms
that are structured into a what we call
a partial information lattice this is
also an
anti-chain an anti-chain lattice for
those of you who are into order Theory
but again you know over here we have the
the two the two Element Case so this is
X1 and X2 predicting information about Y
and here you know we can see this has
the same structure as this V diagram we
have the redundancy down here at the
middle which is subsumed by the unique
uh informations and then we have the
Synergy up at the top right and as the
number of as the number of sources of
information grows the lattice grows you
know super exponentially and you start
to get you know more complicated uh
information theoretic relationships
right so like this little guy that I'm
circling right here is the information
about why that could be learned by
observing X2 or the joint state of X1
and X three okay you know I'm not going
to you know spend too much time dwelling
on these more complicated partial
information atoms but you know the idea
here is that for an arbitrary number of
sources you can decompose the
information uh using this very elegant
lattice structure
okay and so form you know uh if we were
going to uh try to do this all out in
notation what we would say is that we
want a de we have a decomposition that
takes the mutual information that X1 all
the way up to XK dis closes about Y and
decomposes it into a sum of all of these
partial information atoms right and so
math Cal L here is our our calligraphic
L here is the lattice uh each of these
Alpha sub eyes is a vertex on the
lattice and then you know we're
Computing the partial information that
that uh vertex for that atom discloses
about y
okay and so again you know you have a
partial information atom like this this
is the information about why that could
be learned by observing X1 and X2 and X3
or X4 and X5 or
X6 okay there's a certain amount of sort
of detail that I'm kind of elighting
here like how you actually compute the
value of these partial information atoms
I can talk about that at the end but for
our purposes um you don't really need to
know that it's just sort of sufficient
to know that this decomposition exists
and has this form that is connected by
logical ANS and ores
okay so um the p is very powerful it's
very cool I'm a big fan of it uh but it
has a pretty severe limitation that it
requires distinguishing between Source
elements that would be all of these guys
and a single Target element right and
complex systems aren't typically that
nice organized right you know there are
many cases where it doesn't make sense
to say okay what are our sources and
what are our targets we would like to be
able to sort of decompose the structure
of a system qua itself okay and we can
do that um by playing a really fun
little mathematical trick which is um
for a given multivariate system which
I'll denote as bold X which is just you
know X1 through
xn what we're going to do is we're going
to decompose the mutual information that
all of the parts the individual you know
XIs disclose about the whole all right
so here you know our sources our sources
of information are the parts all the
individual variables and then the target
is not some other variable that's
exogenous to them it's actually just
their own joint State and so we know you
know from this basic identity that the
mutual information that all of the parts
disclose about the whole is just the
entropy of the whole and so when we do
the p on this particular Mutual
information we know that all of the
atoms have to sum to the entropy and so
this becomes the partial entropy
decomposition okay this is the
information that all of the parts
disclose about the whole you know of
which they are apart essentially okay
and I spent a lot of time working on
working on this partialy decomposition
um shout out to Robin Inc and Conor Finn
and jier who were working on this a
little bit before me as well and laid
down a lot of the mathematical sort of
fundamentals about this
um and for a long time I was sort of
satisfied with the partial entropy
decomposition because you know it seems
you know to provide this decomposition
of the system qua itself but it still
has now a new limitation it gets rid of
the source Target distinction but the
problem is is that entropy is no longer
really a measure of information right in
the way that we uh introduced it before
right it's more this measure of
uncertainty about the state of the whole
it's not really a reduction in
uncertainty and so for instance you can
see that you know entropy is maximal if
all of the elements are independent of
each other which doesn't really fit our
information intuitions about information
right if entropy is maximal we have
minimal information so it seems kind of
odd that you know our partial entropy
decomposition uh it's not odd I
shouldn't say it makes perfect sense
that the partial entropy decomposition
is you know maximized in the case of
total Independence but that's not really
information you know as we typically
would like it to be all right uh and
so to try to resolve this problem and
really get a a general decomposition of
multivaried information um I turned here
to the kbach Leer Divergence okay and so
the kach Leer Divergence is a nice
Target free definition of um information
and it's actually sort of a
generalization of the classic Shannon
Mutual information in its own right you
know um the uh the Divergence of p p of
x from Q ofx is the amount of
information that you gain when you
update your beliefs about you know the
system X from some prior distribution Q
ofx to a posterior distribution P of X
right and so now we're starting to think
about priors and posteriors again coming
back to this initial definition of
information that um I introduced earlier
right you know in the particular case
where Q ofx is you know the product of
the marginals and P of X is the joint
States you know the C block Lio
Divergence just reduces again back to
the classic Shannon Mutual information
but again we can you know plug in any
prior and any posterior and we still
have a meaningful definition of
information okay so you know my goal
then was to say okay can I take the
partial entropy decomposition which
almost gets us to where I want it to be
and can I somehow remix it so that it
instead of decomposing the entropy
decomposes the cach Leer Divergence
instead and spoilers uh yes we actually
can do that it's not that
hard and so um the the the basic idea
comes down to this uh very simple sort
of algebraic manipulation of the C Le
Divergence right so you know up here we
have it written in terms of you know
something that looks a lot like
Shannon's entropy right you know you
have the sum over all of the uh States
and the support set you know times the
probability of that state then we have
this log ratio P of X over Q ofx okay
this is an expected value um computed
with respect to P of X so I'm just going
to take the summation and the P of X and
I'm just going to shift it out into the
expected value operator and not think
about it again so that leaves us with
the expected value of this log ratio um
by the rules of logs you can split it
apart into a difference of two log logs
and then these two things look a lot
like the uh Shannon information content
right the local entropy and so we can
take these two things and we can
actually rewrite them in terms of um two
different local uh local entropies right
so we ultimately have the difference
between the Shannon information or
surprise of seeing you know this
particular State Little X computed with
respect to the probability distribution
Q minus the uh surprise at seeing this
little state of X computed with respect
to the probability distribution P okay
and so if we go back to thinking about
our priors and our posteriors this looks
very very similar to theistic definition
of information that I gave earlier right
we have the difference between a prior
uncertainty although in this case it's a
local uncertainty or a local
surprise and then this posterior
surprise um attributable to each local
uh local configuration X as well all
right so again this is you know matches
all of our definitions about our
intuitions I should say about
information and you know we can see that
it falls out of the the clock Leo
Divergence very nicely okay and this is
really this is sort of this is the the
most the the Crux of the whole sort of
derivation that I'm doing here right is
that you can recognize that um the C
block Lio Divergence is the expected
value of the difference between two
local entropies which is you know I've
never seen it written out this way
although this is I don't think this
should be surprising to anybody who's
familiar with this um you know it's not
groundbreaking discovery or
anything but um now we can actually
bring in the partial entropy
decomposition that I introduced earlier
right because uh this thing this you
know uh local entropy well we can write
this out as a local Mutual information
you know but now we're just looking at
specific States as opposed to you know
average States but the logic is exactly
the same you know we decompose the sort
of the surprise that all the parts just
close about the whole and we end up with
a localized partial entropy
decomposition that we can apply to every
realization that our system uh X can
adopt and so this gets us to the um kach
leeler Divergence decomposition that I
wanted so you know we start with the
definition it's the expected value of
this difference between two local uh two
local entropies and then we can just use
our local partial entropy decomposition
to decompose each one of these into its
component um Atomic bits essentially and
so we end up for a given uh Atomic
information or information atom the
partial Divergence as we go from to P
from Q is just equal to the expected
value of the partial entropy atoms the
local partial entropy atoms um from the
prior and the posterior all right and
you know because uh this inherits a lot
of the nice properties of the partial uh
partial entropy decomposition we can
then just uh get the original C block
ler Divergence back by summing all of
these partial kach leer divergences over
all of the atoms in the lattice okay and
so I realized that there's been a lot of
notation here a lot of partials and
superscripts and subscripts but you know
really what we're doing is we're just
you know we're computing two different
partial entropy decomposition lates um
so this is the prior lattice and the
posterior lattice and then we're just
subtracting them element wise that's
really what this works out to be um and
you just do this for every possible
state that X can adopt and then average
over um average over all of the states
essentially okay but you know I I I like
to think of it literally just in terms
of subtracting one of these lates from
another I find that it's much uh much
more sort of visually intuitive than um
all of the the symbology and the the
mathematical notation
everything and so that is the
generalized information decomposition
right it's really just the difference
between two uh localized partial entropy
decompositions and so before we sort of
jump into the fun applications are there
any questions about you know what I've
worked through everybody again hanging
on for dear
life yeah that's awesome I definitely
will have questions and I'm sure people
in the chat will too but let's hear
about the generalized information
decomposition then we can get to it
thank you on plugin okay cool um and so
the really nice thing about this
generalized information decomposition is
that any information theoretic measure
that can be written in terms of a cold
block legal Divergence um can now be
decomposed right you know beforehand we
were kind of stuck with like very
special cases right the P works for
multiple sources disclosing information
about one target the partial entropy
decomposition work for the entropy but
now with the G you know any measure that
can be written as a cach webler
Divergence is now fair game so for
instance you know I just picked the
total correlation as kind of an example
it's one of the multivariant
generalizations of the mutual
information and it just generalizes this
idea that we're looking at the
Divergence of the uh the true joint uh
statistics from the product of all the
marginals okay and this is very nice
it's you know zero if all of the
elements are independent and uh in
contrast it's maximal if every x uh
they're all all the elements are copies
of each other essentially um and so that
makes it a very nice um generalization
of the mutual information but it doesn't
really distinguish between lower order
and higher order deviations from
Independence right it doesn't see any
kind of distinction between redundancy
and Synergy that I introduced earlier
but by taking the total correlation and
plugging it into the generalized
information decomposition we can start
to tease out the lower order in the
higher order interactions so for
instance you know um just as an example
I use the logical exclusive or gauge
this sort of a classic example of
synergy in discrete systems the
information that any uh any XI discloses
about Y is just zero bit but then the
information about why that's disclosed
by X1 and X2 is one bit right so this is
pure Synergy the all of the information
about Y is in the ho and not in any of
the parts okay and so if we take this
and we plug it into the generalized
information decomposition uh you'll get
um a lot of zeros but um I just want to
you know bring your attention to this
last column over here so this is the
total correlation and all of the
information here is in this you know the
very tippy top of the lattice you know
the highest the highest order Synergy
term and not anywhere lower okay and so
you know a big table full of zeros is
probably not that exciting but it um
does a really good job I think of
illustrating that you know this G is
sort of is doing what we want it to you
know this is a very good sanity check
that you know yes the Sy The Logical
exor gate is purely synergistic and we
get that back from our generalized
information decomposition and I should
note that I'm using the hmin redundancy
function from um Conor Finn and joier if
that doesn't mean anything to you that's
fine but it's you know
helps describe values to to all of these
okay um similarly um if we have some
measure that is built on multiple C
block leer divergences um you can also
decompose that as well so um here I
looked at the the pretty wellknown ton
sporns Adelman complexity and you know I
won't go into all of the details but the
idea is that it's this measure of
complexity that was designed to be low
both in the case where is just random so
every XI is independent of every other
XJ you know that's kind of like an ideal
gas there's no structure there right you
know so tsse should be low but also when
every XI is just a copy of you know XJ
well then the system is also sort of not
complex but it's crystallized you know
it's it's sort of Highly synchronized
highly redundant very boring and so the
tsse complexity is sort of high in this
interstitial Zone where integration
segregation kind of coexist right and
that sort of matches a lot of our
intuitions about
complexity and then if we but and if so
if we take you know the G and apply it
to each of these total correlations and
then um add and subtract sort of the
sums and differences between these two
uh what we end up with is this really
nice uh decomposition where we can see
that the redundancy so these are all the
these are um total correlation atoms but
I've just you know removed the the total
correlation notation just to make this
visually more accessible you know we can
see that it really penalizes redundancy
right and sort of the more redundant you
are the stronger the the penalty for
being redundant is and then as you climb
up the lattice so you know here the
redundancies at the bottom of the
lattice as you start to climb up
eventually you hit a point of um
increasing Synergy and then suddenly it
starts to reward that Synergy okay and
so we have this very nice transition as
you go from low on the lattice to high
on the lattice you know going from um
penalty to reward and so I think that
this shows us something really
interesting about how the um ton sporns
adalan complexity relates this idea of
you know complexity and integration
segregation balance to uh this idea of
synergy right you know the tsse
complexity was developed like two
decades before we had a really rigorous
understanding of synergy it was not
designed to be a measure of synergy it
was designed to be a measure of
complexity and then it's you know only
now much later that we learn that you
know there seems to be something very
deep linking this idea of balanced
integration segregation to
Synergy okay and so again if you're not
you know super up on the tsse complexity
that's not necessarily like the the main
takeaway here what I'm really trying to
demonstrate is that the G can be used to
give us insights into other measures
right that it can help help us
understand you know what are these
measures telling us in information
theoretic terms okay and there are a ton
of other measures that we could be using
here um and that we could also decompose
in the same way and get sort of similar
insights that's something that I would
be really interested in doing um sort of
in the
future but finally the last thing that I
I wanted to show was that we could
recover the single Target partial
information decomposition from the G
right if the G is a true generalization
of the P we should be able to rec the p
as a special case right we started with
the p we turned it into the partial
entropy decomposition by doing this
weird sort
of thing where we made the Target The
Joint state of all the parts and then
from that we built the uh the G can we
close the loop and go all the way back
to the PID okay and so just to remind
you the PID takes the information that
X1 and X2 just close about Y and breaks
it down into redundant unique and
synergistic component
and then does the same thing for the two
marginal Mutual informations okay and we
recover this from the
G and it turns out that yes you can
right um we can write this uh joint
Mutual information in terms of an
expected value of colbach lier
divergences right and so our prior is
just the uh statistics of X1 and X2
together and then our posterior is the
statistics of X1 and X2 after
conditioning on uh y being in some
particular state right and then so we
compute the expected value of this thing
over all possible uh states that y can
adopt right and so this just works out
to Computing you know you know a bunch
of a bunch of lates essentially um Two
element lates because we have you know
two two variables X1 and X2 and then we
just average you know so if we were to
take the expected value of all of the
top latest Synergy terms we would get
the the P Synergy back you know if we
were to take the average or the expected
value over all of the uh redundancy the
redundancies down here at the bottom we
would get the P redundancy back okay and
uh this does Recapture the partial
information decomposition as we would
expect if you use the H Min redundancy
function for your generalized
information decomposition you get the P
ID back that uses the imen redundant
function for the partial information
decomposition so you know we can see
very clearly how the the entropy terms
turn into the uh information terms okay
and that all sort of looks well and good
and I was you know pretty happy to be
putting a bow on this project until I
realized that there is another way that
you can write the uh joint Mutual
information out as a CB mular
Divergence and that's this way right so
you know we can also write the same
thing out as the uh cach leer Divergence
from a prior which is the product of you
know the probability of X1 and X2 times
the product times the probability of Y
and then the uh the posterior is our
joint States okay but this requires
decomposing a three-dimensional
probability distribution PX probility of
X1 X2 and Y whereas before we only ever
were composing two variable probability
distributions okay so this is why you
know in this case we had an nice Four
Element lce here we're actually
decomposing a threedimensional
probability distribution and so the
resulting lattice will have 18 uh
partial entropy at or partial
information atoms rather than four right
so we're going to end up with this uh
decomposition of the joint Mutual
information as opposed to the expected
Four Element composition okay and I I I
spent a long time trying to you know
find some way that I could squish this
uh 18 element lattice back down into the
Four Element lates that I sort of you
know expected to get and I was not
successful um the people who
peer-reviewed the paper were also um you
know didn't have any suggestions either
so I won't say that it can't be done but
if there is a way to do it it is
currently Beyond me um and so this sort
of puts us in a little bit of a pickle
right like we would expect the
decomposition we would expect a unique
decom I want to maybe not say expect we
would hope that there would be a unique
decomposition for a single um Mutual
information right uh it's kind of odd
that you can take one mutual information
and depending on how you like choose to
denote it you know how you choose to
write out the C Divergence you could end
up with two sort of
non-identical uh non interconvertible
decompositions so what's happening here
like this was very odd to me um and so
my working Theory and this is just a
theory if any other mathematicians are
in the audience and want to want to take
a stab at it you're more than welcome to
I think what's actually happening is
that you know these two ways of writing
out the joint Mutual information are
actually sort of fundamentally different
right in the first case we're looking at
a three-way interaction right we're
looking at the case of the interaction
between X1 and X2 and Y okay whereas in
the second case um we are sort of
abstracting Y out or sort of removing it
from the Divergence and um sort of
wrapping it all in this expectation
value of y okay and so what you're doing
here is you're actually like these are
two different kinds of dependencies
right they're mathem ially
interconvertible and they'll always
resolve to the same value when you plug
in numbers but they are in some
fundamental way different kinds of
structure in the system right and so uh
the classic Shannon information Theory
sort of can't see this difference right
it just says oh you know these two
things can be you know algebraically
turned into each other and therefore
they must be the same but actually kind
of under the hood um they are you know
two different ways of looking at this
interaction between X1 X2 and Y and so
again classic Shannon information Theory
can't see this difference but the
information decomposition can and I sort
of should note that this is not the
first time this is sort of um Turned Up
there are a couple of other cases where
classic Shannon information theory has
been unable to see a distinction between
two you know categories of object but
you know when you start looking at the
information decomposition suddenly you
can
okay I'm sure there's a lot more to say
about this um and I'd be interested in
talking to people about it after the
fact but you know I'll just sort of
leave you with this question now of sort
of non-identical decompositions of the
same
value and let's see I think I'm coming
to the end of my my time here so I want
to talk just a little bit about um sort
of possible applications and some future
work that I would like to do and I'd be
happy to collaborate with u with other
people uh with as well and so um I think
that this uh sort of is a big step
towards um what I call like a grand
unified theory of multivaried
information right you know we have this
sort of interesting case where you have
you know the we started with the PID
right and then from the PID we can
construct you know the partial entropy
decomposition right the peed is a
special case of the p and then from the
PED the partial entropy decomposition we
can construct the generalized
information
decomposition right and then we can take
the generalized information
decomposition and we can re-extract the
partial information
decomposition from it with sort of these
weird caveats right and so you know this
kind of you know aoris sort of thing
where we have all of these different
information decompositions that are kind
of fundamentally built out of each other
I think is really you know getting it
something fundamental with how we can
think about sort of these part hole
relationships um in multivariate uh
multivariate systems um the last thing
that I sort of haven't been able to do
is incorporate um the integrated
information decomposition and so this
was proposed by um Ked manano and
Fernando roses and you know other people
uh at um in England uh I'm not sure
where everybody is now um but you know
this uh they provided a very very
elegant generalization of the P that
allows you to have multiple sources and
multiple targets um and so you know I
would really like to be able to find a
way to incorporate that into this um
this P ped G framework for sort of a
truly brand unified theory of
multivariate information decomposition
um still working on that open to
collaborating with anybody who's also
interested in taking that project on um
and then finally so let's let's talk
about predictive coding because this is
an active inference stream and so um I
assume everybody is sort of familiar
with the basic idea of predictive coding
that the that the brain is sort of
acting as a kind of basian inference
engine right you know it has a world
model it has some set of beliefs about
the world and it updates those beliefs
you know um as it navigates through it
and receives sensory stimuli okay U and
so you know one of the things that I'm
really interested in is you know how
might this predictive information about
the environment be redundantly or
synergistically distributed over
different sensory channels right like
we're not just learning you know we
don't just have Vision right you know we
have Vision we have hearing we have
touch we have propr reception there are
other animals that have senses that are
totally alien to us and so when we take
in all of that sensory information and
build a world model you know we can't
just treat every one of these incoming
information streams as independent of
everyone else right we are uh have to
learn you know these complex higher
order interactions between different
incoming streams of sensory information
and we use that to build a really rich
World model okay and so a great example
that I first heard from Andrea lupy uh
who is um you know a friend and sort of
collaborator of mine you know he was
talking to me about stereoscopic depth
perception right for this is sort of an
example of synergy between two incoming
sensory channels right if you cover one
eye you lose the ability to perceive you
know depth right so there's you know
redundant information you know that you
know both eyes get simultaneously
there's unique information that you know
sort of at the corners of your visual
field and then finally you have Synergy
which is the this sort of emergent
perception of depth this qualia of you
know receding distance that you only get
when you're getting information from the
right eye and the left eye
simultaneously right so from sort of a
cognitive modeling standpoint our
ability to extract sort of higher order
information from multip multiple
incoming sensory channels is clearly
very relevant to our perception and our
behavior in the
world and so you know I'm I'm sort of
tempted to propose you know a hypothesis
of Maximum Synergy right so you know if
there are two different channels that
are totally redundant right you know an
agent that only has you know some
minimal number of calories that it can
burn you know keeping itself alive isn't
going to want to spend calories you know
perceiving both uh both senses
independently right like all the
information you get get from one you can
get from the other so you know why spend
money on both right but in contrast if
there's you know synergistic information
in in X1 and X2 that you can only get
when both are present well then modeling
or having channels to you know sense all
of them becomes essential right and if
it's truly synergistic then you know
having just X1 on its own or just X2 on
its own may not be you know giving you
any information you know it's you know
if there's Synergy in the environment
then you need to you know spend calories
maintaining both pass both channels and
so you know my guess is that there's
probably some kind of evolutionary
pressure that says you know agents with
limited resources and complex
environments probably want to maximize
the number of synergies that they are
sensitive to when building their world
model while simultaneously minimizing
the redundancies right so the
redundancies are basically just waste of
calories while the synergies are you
know potentially very in ative you know
higher order interactions that are well
worth the calories and so this is about
as far as I've gotten on this hypothesis
but I think it would be something really
interesting to explore uh down the line
you know maybe either in very simple
animal models or in some kind of in
silico minimally conscious or not
minimally conscious minimally cognitive
agent kind of approach and again that's
something that I would love to talk um
to really anybody else about and then so
you know that's sort of the end of my
shiel here this is the paper was
published in plus one um couple of
months ago you know here is the link and
I'll I'll send around the slides um
afterwards if anybody wants them I can
send them to Dan uh hopefully yeah um
and yeah so so that's it this is work
that I sort of largely did on my own so
I don't have the usual sort of
acknowledgement slides but I'll just um
say Let's uh jump right to questions and
I'd love to get feedback from anybody
else on the work what you might think
about it or what your own thoughts might
be
awesome thank you for the very very
clear great
presentation lot of places to jump in
could you speak a little bit about
redundancy and Synergy with respect to
fragility and other system properties
because having redundancy although like
as you brought up in those last slides
it might cost more energy and so in the
short term it might appear like well why
do we need to have redundant information
when there are like component failures
or other kinds of perturbations to the
system what's redundant in one moment
might come to be not redundant so how do
you think about these kind of
informational properties of systems or
networks with respect to other systems
properties so that's a great question
and I'd be curious who asked it because
I actually just put up a preprint about
exactly that exactly that topic so I I
don't know if they're aware of it so
yeah that's a really good question you
know um redundancy and Synergy how do
they relate to things like fragility and
robustness um I don't I don't have
slides for this but I can give you just
sort of the verbal um
tldr uh I I just did this project where
we took um very simple Boolean
networks and uh I evolved them either to
be uh very redundant or very synergistic
and then since Boolean networks you know
there's a lot of ways to characterize
their Dynamics I ask sort of what are
the Dynamics that kind of come along
with Evolution for redundancy or
Evolution for Synergy and what I found
was that the the Redundant Boolean
networks were extremely stable right you
know you could perturb them and they
would almost always fall back to you
know one of a very small number of
attractors you know they had very
restricted State spaces they were kind
of crystallized okay um in contrast the
synergistic networks were um basically
chaotic it was very hard to find ways in
which they did not just appear to be you
know chaotic systems you know using
chaos in the sort of the technical sense
here of sort of sensitive dependence on
initial conditions you know very large
State spaces lots of you know attractors
you know small perturbations sent them
off onto very different you know
possible futures um
and the you know the the punchline then
was that you know if we took these two
different networks then asked you know
about their capacity to um integrate
information and I Ed this measure of
integrated information from integrated
information Theory you know what I found
was that the synergistic networks could
integrate lots of information whereas
the Redundant networks were very stable
but could not integrate information at
all right so there was sort of this this
you know when you were at the extremes
you could you know be very stable and
totally unable to integrate information
or you could be hilariously unstable
with lots of integrated information
right um and
so the last thing that I tried then was
I actually then evolved networks that
had you know this this the the TSE
complexity that I mentioned before you
know this this um balance of integration
and segregation and what I found was
actually that the complex networks were
able to sort of split this difference
right you know they were sort of they
were more stable than the purely
synergistic networks you know they
weren't as chaotic but they also had you
know more capacity to integrate
information than the crystalized
networks right so you know we proposed
this kind of um sort of multi-way
tradeoff where redundancy brings
stability but restricts your ability to
integrate information whereas Synergy
you know brings integrative capacity but
is destabilizing or fragilized and then
you can kind of balance those two things
with this idea of complexity that you
know brings together integration and
segregation in a kind of you know sort
of modular a modular structure and so
that's been sitting under review at um
chaos for like the last six months they
have no idea what they're doing over
there um but hopefully uh you know we
will you know that will be impressed
before um the end of my postto hopefully
and I would you know there's a lot of
work that I want to do um going on sort
of trying to build on that as well so
great question that's awesome I mean
you've approached from very
informational first oh sorry you've
approached it from very informational
first principles and recovered a lot of
these topological and dynamical features
of complex systems and how they have to
trade off against these like multiple
properties of systemness that sometimes
might be like directly contradictory um
a question in the live chat Celeste
wrote How might G be related with
network controlability
Ah that's a really good question and um
I'm G I'll be honest I have no idea um
uh Network control theory is something
that i' you know I'm I'm a consumer of
network control theory I'm not a
producer you know so I'll see these
papers you know like Parker Singleton
had a great one looking at um like
Network control theory and you know LSD
and siloc cybin I was like oh that's
really cool but I don't I don't know
enough about the theory to really get at
it um I my guess just sort of just off
the cuff would be that redundancy would
make the
network perhaps less controllable
because you know it always wants to fall
back into you know like its main
attractor whereas Synergy you know
probably lowers the energy needed to um
you know push you onto a different you
know part of the configuration space but
you know it's maybe less stable maybe
more fragile so so I I I think that this
is a great case where um you know some
some simple toy models maybe some
analysis of um fmri data could go a long
way to you know answering a really
interesting question question um but I
you know I can't say for certain other
than just sort of those very sort of
handwavy predictions but I'd love to see
it I'd love to see it done cool yeah one
thing that you brought at the ends with
the two eyes looking at the object and
getting depth it really made me think
about the multiple scales of redundant
and synergistic information like you
have two photo receptors that are right
next to each other so just from a first
past correlational value it would seem
like they're going to be highly
correlated sensors I mean they're in a
sensor array like on the retina and yet
also the differences between retinal
receptors are used to improve like
signal to noise characteristics at
multiple um steps in the relay of visual
processing then you have the two eyes
and depth perception and then there's
also cross modal synergistic information
like maybe if you just saw the video of
somebody or only heard what they had to
say it might convey certain information
and yet putting them together that is
very important for understanding like
well how do different kinds of
multi-modal experiences convey
information about real world things and
for cognitive modeling like of
biological systems or design of
cognitive systems these kinds of
redundancies and synergy would basically
be ignored at one's Peril because you
can always describe kind of the
syntactic flow of information and say
like this is how much data at each
moment we're pushing through this
connectivity but that might be
misleading or fragile or overdesigned or
underes with respect to relatively
obvious intuitive ways in which we fuse
[Music]
path of a given cognitive entity because
while you're able to represent all the
possible partitions and like you as a
mathematician can can pick up that and
handle it we might um from like an
attentional networks in the brain
perspective we might ask like well which
node on this lattice should we be
looking at like should how should we
blend the indicators from person one and
two to the um exclusion of three or two
and three but not one those are like
different attentional modes you can have
and you could have a uniform prior
across that lattice and just say well
we're going to blur across all them but
then once you start saying oh but I like
this one and this one's irrelevant and
these two are the same then you're
getting into the business of reshaping
the portfolio across the lattice and
then that how do we deal with that when
outside of dealing with these systems
purely symbolically we actually want to
be using certain partitions and and
identifying useful um decomposed
components like how do you think about
that well so I mean first thing is you
know you mentioned time again I again
want to shout out um Pedro and Fernando
and Andreas work on integrated
information decomposition because they
really you know I introduced it as this
like multiple sources multiple targets
but they have this incredibly cool um
application of that where they say okay
well all the sources
[Music]
nobody has ever like computed it right
um so finding ways to kind of you know
figure out you know how how do we get
sort of the
information how do we make this
information accessible to us as
modelers you know is like sort of sort
of an outstanding problem as well um
which is kind I think kind of getting
what you're saying and then the other
thing is that like as the lattice gets
bigger the the particular atoms become
like
hilariously Arcane right it's like okay
what information could be learned by
observing X1 and X2 and X9 and X10 or X1
and X2 and X3 and X9 or X1 and X2 and X7
you know like you end up with these
incredibly long chains of logical
dependencies that you know my guesses
almost certainly don't mean anything
right and so again figuring out some way
to extract or just decide what are the
meaningful dependencies right not just
like what are all of the dependencies
you know as a mathematician I like
completeness right I like having the
whole the whole pie but you know again
outside of that you know the question of
how do we figure out what information is
sort of relevant to us um that's that I
think is a standing problem you know I
think there's a lot of space there for
Creative you know attacks um on the
question because there isn't you know i'
I've taken my own swing at it other
people have as as well I think you know
again there's a lot of sort of work
still to be done in that space and it's
very exciting to see what people will
come up with in the coming you know next
five 10
years yeah few thoughts on that first I
think what you said there about even
with 10 retinal receptors or like an
insect eye with multiple iddia like once
you get to 10 enumerating the lattice is
is not even finitely accomplishable and
I think that in a way must speak to the
relevance of coar graining and nesting
of models because you couldn't you you
couldn't have 10 people in a room and
all those par wise combinations happen
so like there has to be some clustering
and and nesting um and then also that um
what you said about the specific atoms
being like hilariously Arcane reminded
me of random Forest modeling and you
also had the kind of logical framework
so then it's sort of like tell me
either your favorite cereal and what
color of this car you would want or this
and that and like the concept is yeah
those are drawn from a massive State
space of possible thresholds or or
choices yet through statistics and
iteration some of those
thresholds May identify kind of
critical decision points with within an
empirical State space which is probably
going to be existing on like manifolds
or subspaces that don't require the full
unpacking of the lattice but there might
be whole like territories of the lattice
that you can just average over but the
question is how nicely are those
distributed on the whole lattice if
those are distributed randomly then
there may not be many ways to work with
it but if those are all on one side then
a random for
with a simple first question might like
bring one into a useful
area yeah that's a really interesting
idea I never thought about the link to
random Forest before but I'm going to
write that down and um you know take a
stab at I like that a lot cool yeah um I
guess one of the interesting questions
too is
information for whom and about what
like in the yeah in the math that's kind
of generalized over appropriately
so but then when we're constructing
active inference models and we're
actually using the K Divergence like in
the variational free energy where the K
Divergence is used like in the
complexity minus accuracy way to talk
about it or when we're using K
Divergence in the expected free energy
prospective setting thinking about like
the Divergence between what we prefer
for observations and for how we think
different kinds of courses of action are
going to play out looking at those
divergences it does get very
specific what we're talking about the
reduction with respect
to so how how do you bring something
that's kind of generalized
across observers and types of variables
and bring that from being kind of an
analytical result into being something
like the air conditioner is reducing the
K Divergence about preferred
temperatures with respect to courses of
air
conditioning what happens between having
this math and being able to use it in
those
settings so so that's that's a really
good question and you know like again
coming from a math perspective like I'm
always like gunning for full generality
right like the less useful this is like
the happier I am but you know like it
like the G really is just you know it is
a a decomposition of the KL Divergence
right like all of the the general stuff
is kind of you know it's sort of an
added bonus so you know you could have a
KL Divergence where you know your prior
and your posterior are very well defined
right you're like I know exactly what my
prior is I know exactly what my
posterior is I know exactly how to
interpret it and then you can just go
ahead and you know crank the G handle
and you know you'll get the
decomposition back out so I think you
know the you know the again I approach
it from sort of the general perspective
but if you want to sort of take it and
make it specific you know that's I
there's no I think fundamental
mathematical problem with that it's
really just a question of you know how
to what extent can you specify exactly
sort of what your priors and posteriors
are and how you then interpret the
resulting numbers right because the G
itself doesn't care about the
interpretation it just says like we have
one distribution we have another
distribution and like they have this
structure that relates them but you know
if you you know have your interpretation
and your you know sort of let's say
maybe domain knowledge that sort of
specifies everything then yeah I think
that that's you know that the generality
is not necessarily a problem you know
how would you
connect this to the concept of like
known unknowns and unknown
unknowns oh boy um so the problem with
information theory is that it it has it
has a very hard time with unknown
unknowns right like it kind of assumes
that you have the
distributions you know that you have all
of the the distribute
like how do I how do I say this this is
a little a little
bit
um getting a little Tongue Tied here so
you know the from the perspective of the
K Divergence like all it sees is what's
in the distribution right you know and
you know so you plug the distributions
in you turn the the math crank and you
get numbers out there's not an obvious
or real way I think to account for the
possibility that there is sort of you
know meta uncertainty right like you can
be uncertain about you know what's
probability of X1 what's the probability
of X2 right but there's you know what is
the pro like how are like how certain
are you about these certainties that's
something that as far as I know you know
the sort of vanilla information theory
that I'm familiar with really actually
really quite struggles with you know and
I I'm really interested in in climate
science and climate change kind of stuff
and you know I keep running into this
idea of like deep uncertainty right like
how you know what's the probability that
your probability distrib tion is
actually the right one you know and
that's like there's I think some very
cool work happening in that space But
it's you know a step or two Beyond you
know what what I what I think can be
tackled with what I've presented here so
I guess I I don't know um I think that
that's something that we've got to work
work
on yeah that's that's super interesting
it reminds me even back in learning
about like the mean and the variance of
a distribution it's like Okay so we've
parameterized our uncertainty about the
mean and we called that the variance but
then how certain are we or how do we get
a P value on the uncertainty and then in
the hierarchical basian modeling
approach you can just keep on going but
the Buck has to stop
somewhere and then you can go to kind of
another set of methods and pick
different prior distributions for that
highest possible prior um or take other
approaches but that's like a very kind
of composite
approach that is not necessarily
returning back down to the Simplicity of
of the initial question you're just
getting into like higher orders like
what if there what is the probability
that there was another element that we
were
missing and then that but that could um
in increase the complexity of the
problem so much that even a simple
question would be kind of like
unnecessarily
exploded because of even a very small
probability of something happening that
changes the state space of the initial
question very greatly and then that
would kind of like potentially um forego
a lot of lwh hanging fruit to kind of
cover the bases against some rare events
which still might not even be detected
because you would have just basically
turned some kind of unknown unknown into
a Known
Unknown but at expensive
cost and making the problem quite
different so it's kind of like is that
something that can be resolved in an
airtight way or is that kind of like the
openness that just requires
iterated
engagement yeah I mean my my my sort of
my intuition is always you know sort of
keep things as simple as possible you
know but not too simple like that the
quote the quote says you know I I
I in in the paper I write a lot about
like all of the contexts in which you
shouldn't use the G right that was like
something that I spent a lot of time on
and so you know the K Lio Divergence
does have sort of these odd limitations
or for instance you know anywhere that
you know Q of X is zero you know where
you know you have a you know something
happens in the posterior that you didn't
think could happen the prior like the
whole thing blows up right and so I do
think that if you wanted to use this in
an analytical context you know or in a
practical context not just a theoretical
one you know would require a lot of
thoughts about like is this actually the
right tool you know for the question
that I want to answer you know and it's
entirely possible that no it's not the G
the p is not the right tool for you know
a system where or you have you know
changing support sets you know or
unknown unknowns and and that's fine you
know there's you know plenty of
mathematical um toys in the Box for us
to play with and so I guess like my
response to that would be like if you
find yourself asking those questions
like maybe just don't use the G or the P
ID maybe there's something else that
would be a more appropriate uh
appropriate tool for your question
H that Al Al makes me think about
like the concept of I guess different
ways to approach it but like information
or or stimuli that have an informational
impact information cannot be negative
per se yet there are ways to move
distributions up and down and then there
are ways in which the movement of that
distribution up or down would have like
an adaptivity benefit or detriment to an
organism so
information is just kind of at this
level this is um coming in lower in the
processing that it it is not necessarily
a complete answer to questions about
complex
systems however it helps ground and
anchor some subsequent questions about
their higher order Dynamics in a way
that skipping
[Music]
just we'll wait a minute if anyone in
the chat has any last questions but I
mean where and how are you going to take
it
forward so I'm really interested you
know I've spent most of my PhD I kind of
spent working on like the mathematics of
these things you know I wrote about the
peed I wrote about this you know I've
worked on some other stuff I'm really
curious about like where can this be
applied to real data right and so know
I'm working currently I'm at the
University of Vermont I'm working with
Josh bongard and Mike 11 on um some sort
of interesting projects in like
evolutionary Computing and evolutionary
biology to see like you know where are
these you know are are these synergies
in nature and are they telling us
anything about the the sort of behavior
or structure of organisms you know I'm
still interested in Neuroscience you
know um I sort of a long-standing
interest in like psychedelic
neuroscience and so you know whether
there are changes to redundancies and
synergies in the brain you know when
you're you know on DMT or whatever uh
could that help explain why phenomenal
logical Consciousness changes that's
something I've worked on um before as
well and so really trying to find ways
to get out of like sort of math Theory
land and see like does this actually
tell us something about nature as
opposed to just like the structure of
information theory is sort of what I'd
like to do um next although that's also
expensive and requires data whereas pure
Theory just needs a whiteboard and a a
latte compiler so it's a lower
overhead just on that kind of like
Altered States Of Consciousness and and
um and all of those possibilities it's
almost
like
what what
decompositions help one like gain
knowledge about thems or about something
else and it might be like a
decomposition of like this amount of
that in this setting or this amount in
that
setting provide information
on a a common Target
distribution and that Maps out like an
architecture that's not this part of the
brain's connected to that one it's not
even necessarily the architecture of
kind of like the dynamic causal modeling
of the
neuroanatomy but it really would be
toward like architectures of beliefs and
how they have different equivalences or
or relationships
yeah there's um there's a really
interesting uh set of papers by Robin
carard Harris and Carl friston looking
at sort of a free energy or a basian
approach to like psychedelic therapy
like how do our beliefs change and how
does you know tickling these serotonin
receptors change our change our beliefs
and so I think that would be a really
interesting place to try to um apply
something like this if you could get
like meaningful p's and q's right like
you know if you're looking at something
like you know post-traumatic stress
disorder right you know you're changing
your beliefs not just about like the
world around you but also like your own
interor reception you know is the
capacity to you know heal from trauma or
something does that require a higher
order a synergistic you know change in
sort of the joint states of your beliefs
about the world and yourself that is
sort of not trivially reducible to like
just tweaking one or tweaking the other
right and so you know getting into sort
of more of this um sort of cognitive
cognitive kind of stuff I think would be
really interesting I also you know one
one thing I I didn't mention when we
talk about future stuff is one that I've
been working on quite recently is you
know the the P and the peed you know
it's all gamed out currently in terms of
entropies and mutual informations but as
long as you have a function a general
function that satisfies certain axioms
you know non- negativity um you know mon
picity yada yada yada you can also get a
lattice and you can also do like the
mobious inversion and get the
decomposition so I've been working a lot
on you
know taking you know what I'm calling
sort of like structure decomposition
like if you have a network you know you
know and you have a measure like the
communicability which does satisfy all
of the sort of the the desidera to
induce a decompos information
decomposition you could do a
communicability decomposition right
looking at like the influence of edges
or nodes to this measure the
communicability instead of the
information you know or you could look
at the shortest path efficiency this one
also satisfies all of those requirements
and so you know can we take these
logical mathematical structures that
were developed in the context of
information and entropy and apply them
to other things you know um I'm looking
I'm a network guy by training so I'm
looking at Network measures now but you
know could you how far could you push
this right could you start looking at
maybe psychological constructs could you
start looking at you know dynamical
properties like
the I don't know
the I having a stroke I'm drawing a
blank on any good dynamical properties
but you you get the sort of the idea of
what I'm you know what I'm trying to say
like how far can we push this logical
structure to look at higher order
interactions in other contexts that are
information
theoretic
yes that just makes me feel like
networks give a discretized and
topological handle on families of
continuous phenomena or the phenomena
could be discreet at the node level but
we could just be talking about a
continuous statistical distribution so
that at the node level gives us
continuity and connection with empirical
data and statistics and then the math
picks up up with these
discretized
lates and kind of like studying a tree
is like studying a tree and then you
pull back and you have a model of the
forest and then what could you know by
studying two trees well they could be
giving redundant information they could
be giving synergistic information about
what and then it's kind of like off one
goes on that
inquiry yeah huge potential there I
think for a lot of really cool sort of
new ways of thinking about complex
systems awesome um if you have any last
comments feel free to go for it
otherwise this has been epic and very
informative um you know all I'll say is
you know you can find me uh you can find
me on Twitter you know you can you know
my you can find me on my my email um you
know I'm always open I don't know how
many people are on the on the YouTube
right now but I was I'm always open to
like collaboration talking to people you
know like I am you know if any of this
is interesting to you shoot me an email
please and I would be happy to talk you
know about any and all of this like my
inbox is open so I look forward to
hearing from folks thank you for that
and thank you again for joining so till
10.2 see you
bye
e